<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/preview.xsl"?>
<!-- Time-stamp: "2016-02-01 18:36:22 ashley"-->
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#x2014;">
  <!ENTITY ndash "&#x2013;">
  <!ENTITY conduit "<code>conduit</code>">
  <!ENTITY us "_">
  <!ENTITY tilde "~">
  <!ENTITY bar "|">
]>
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  
  <head>
    <title>OpenAPI version 0.3</title>
    <subtitle>Improving the OpenAPI architecture</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <author>
	<name>Ashley Noel Hinton</name>
	<email>ahin017@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      </author>
      <author>
	<name>Paul Murrell</name>
	<email>paul@stat.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      </author>
      <affiliation>Department of Statistics, The University of
      Auckland</affiliation>
    </authors>
    <date>4 February, 2016</date>
    <description>Technical report about improvements to OpenAPI in
    versions 0.2 and 0.3.</description>
  </head>

  <body>
    <section class="contents">
      <xi:include parse="xml" href="contents.xml">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude contents.xml</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </section>

    <section>
      <h1 class="unnumbered">Introduction</h1>

      <p>The OpenAPI project aims to help people connect with
      data. OpenAPI is a software architecture for wrapping component
      pieces of data analysis&mdash;datasets, programming scripts,
      etc.&mdash;in reusable modules. These simple modules can be
      combined in pipelines which describe more complex data analysis
      workflows. Modules and pipelines are created in XML, and
      executed in software called a glue system. This report details
      the improvements made to the OpenAPI architecture between
      versions 0.1 and 0.3.</p>

      <p>Version 0.1 of the OpenAPI architecture introduced the
      OpenAPI module XML specification for wrapping data analysis
      scripts. The XML specification for modules was not well-suited
      to wrapping scripts which had not been written with OpenAPI in
      mind. This report describes the changes made to the OpenAPI
      architecture in version 0.3. These changes include the
      introduction of `vessel' elements for describing inputs and
      outputs to OpenAPI modules which improve the authoring of module
      and pipeline XML. This report also describes the introduction of
      a module `host' machine which allows OpenAPI to address issues
      concering software dependencies; these issues affect the
      portability and reproducibility of data analysis
      workflows. Version 0.3 of the OpenAPI architecture also
      introduces XML Schema for module and pipeline XML, allowing
      module and pipeline authors to validate their files.</p>

      <p>This report demonstrates how the changes introduced in
      OpenAPI v0.3 make it much easier for module authors to wrap
      `wild' data analysis scripts in OpenAPI modules. This report
      provides examples of how OpenAPI can be used to execute data
      analysis code from external scripts, and even from blog
      posts. The report demonstrates how executing `wild' source
      scripts using OpenAPI maintains a connection to the original
      script sources, while also allowing a module or pipeline author
      to extend or adapt the scripts she wraps. Wrapping data analysis
      scripts in module XML also allows a module author to archive
      versions of a script against the sometimes ephemeral nature of
      online resources.</p>

      <p>The OpenAPI pipelines and modules described in this report
      were all created, tested and executed in &conduit;, a prototype
      OpenAPI glue system implemented as an R package. The &conduit;
      package source code is available online at
      <url>https://github.com/anhinton/conduit</url>. The &conduit;
      package was also improved as part of this project: these changes
      were implemented in version 0.3 of &conduit;, which available
      for download at
      <url>https://github.com/anhinton/conduit/releases/tag/v0.3</url>.
      </p>

      <p>This report may give the impression that OpenAPI and
      &conduit; have made the leap from version 0.1 to 0.3 without any
      mention of version 0.2. Many of the changes in this report were
      implemented in version 0.2 of OpenAPI and &conduit; (<cite
      key="hinton2015conduit02">Hinton, 2015b</cite>). However, as
      version 0.3 represents a more fully realised implementation of
      the changes described here, only version 0.3 is mentioned
      within.</p>
      
      <h2>Outline</h2>

      <p>The following outline should serve as a map to the various
      sections of this report:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><a href="#sec-background">Background</a>: The first section of
	this report provides some context for the aims of the OpenAPI
	project. This section also describes the composition of the
	OpenAPI architecture, and how its pieces interact.</li>
	<li><a href="#sec-problems-in-openapi-version-0.1">Problems in
	OpenAPI version 0.1</a>: the second section of this report
	describes the problems identified in the XML specification of
	OpenAPI v0.1. This section also describes the difficulties of
	wrapping data analysis scripts which were not written
	specifically for OpenAPI, i.e. almost every data analysis
	script in the `wild'. The XML examples in this section were
	written using OpenAPI v0.1.</li>
	<li><a href="#sec-changes-in-openapi-version-0.3">Changes in
	OpenAPI version 0.3</a>: this section details the changes in
	the OpenAPI XML specification found in version 0.3. This
	section demonstrates improvements over OpenAPI v0.1 using XML
	examples. Each change to OpenAPI is followed by a module or
	pipeline example to illustrate the improvement.</li>
	<li><a href="#sec-running-wild-source-scripts">Running `wild'
	source scripts</a>: This section provides examples of how the
	improvements in OpenAPI v0.3 make it easier to wrap source
	scripts, including those found embedded in other
	documents. These examples also demonstrate how OpenAPI v0.3
	makes it possible to subset and modify `wild' data analysis
	scripts while preserving connections to original scripts. The
	examples in this section demonstrate the changes and
	improvements made in OpenAPI v0.3.</li>
	<li><a href="#appendix-technical-requirements">Technical
	requirements</a>: Details of the system used to execute the
	pipeline and module examples contained in this report.</li>
	<li><a href="#appendix-pipeline-examples">Pipeline
	examples</a>: Full pipeline and module examples used in the
	report, including code for executing the pipelines in
	&conduit; v0.3, and final output.</li>
      </ul>

    </section>

    <section id="sec-background">
      <h1>Background</h1>

      <p>As the world collects and makes available more and more data
      it is increasingly important for people to be able to access,
      understand and use this data to make decisions in their
      lives. Government initiatives like the New Zealand Government
      Open Access and Licensing framework (NZGOAL), and data.gov.uk
      have made more government and public data available online
      (<cite key="dia2011declaration">Department of Internal Affairs,
      2011</cite>; <cite key="cabinetoffic2010government">Cabinet
      Office, 2010</cite>).</p>

      <p>Almost all newly available data is provided online digitally,
      in a variety of proprietary and open file formats; these files
      can be read into various commercial and open software
      applications where the user can manipulate the data, perform
      analyses on them, and produce various summaries and graphics
      describing the data. A key challenge in helping people to
      connect with data is that even with freely accessible data and
      freely available software tools the data user still needs a host
      of skills to make use of the data, and of the tools. Hinton and
      Murrell (<cite key="hinton2015introducing">2015a</cite>) suggest
      that, as well as access to data, the following are required for
      people to fully connect with data:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>domain knowledge: a data user cannot make use of data if she
	does not have a contextual understanding of where the data comes
	from and what it means;</li>
	<li>data science skills: a data user must know what analytical
	tools are available and how they can be used to examine data
	sets;</li>
	<li>statistical graphics skills: a data user must know what
	graphical tools are available, and how they can be used to
	explore the characteristics of the data;</li>
	<li>graphical design skills: a data user must know how to
	produce meaningful graphics which do not mislead the reader, and
	which meet graphical design and presentation norms.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>It is understandably very rare to find someone who is the
      master of all of these skills, however, and it is perhaps too
      demanding to expect an everyday person to be expert in even one
      of these categories. One solution to this problem is to design
      software which provides many of these skills for the user, and
      which allows users to share what skills they have with other
      users. OpenAPI takes a different approach; as described in
      Hinton (<cite key="hinton2015helping">2015a</cite>) the OpenAPI
      architecture is designed to help solve this problem by
      being:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>modular,</li>
	<li>reusable,</li>
	<li>shareable,</li>
	<li>extensible,</li>
	<li>open and free,</li>
	<li>not overly technical,</li>
	<li>not monolithic, and,</li>
	<li>compatible with reproducible research.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Perhaps most importantly, the OpenAPI architecture is
      intended to make it easy to incorporate existing resources, like
      data analysis scripts, without the authors of these scripts
      having to be aware of OpenAPI at all.</p>

      <h2>The OpenAPI architecture</h2>

      <p>The OpenAPI architecture consists of XML specifications for
      `module' and `pipeline' files: module XML files wrap scripts of
      programming code which describe tasks in data analysis; pipeline
      XML files describe how to connect and combine the inputs and
      outputs from several modules as a data workflow. The OpenAPI
      architecture also specifies requirements for software which can
      create, interpret, and execute modules and pipelines; an
      instance of such software is called a `glue system' (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">Hinton &amp; Murrell,
      2015a</cite>).</p>

      <p>A <code>&lt;module&gt;</code> is the smallest piece in the
      OpenAPI system. A module XML file wraps a data script, specifies
      the platform or language in which this script can be executed,
      and names the inputs required and the outputs produced by this
      script (<cite key="hinton2015introducing">Hinton &amp; Murrell,
      2015a</cite>).</p>

      <p>A <code>&lt;pipeline&gt;</code> XML file describes how a
      module's outputs are to be connected to the inputs of other
      modules; the output of one module can be provided as the input
      of another module through a <code>&lt;pipe&gt;</code>
      element. Executing a pipeline results in the execution of all
      the wrapped module scripts contained within (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">Hinton &amp; Murrell,
      2015a</cite>).</p>

      <p>Modules and pipelines are executed by a software `glue
      system'. An OpenAPI glue system is responsible for ensuring that
      a module's inputs are satisfied, and that its outputs can be
      resolved. The glue system is responsible for providing one
      module's output as another module's inputs as described by a
      pipeline XML file (<cite key="hinton2015introducing">Hinton
      &amp; Murrell, 2015a</cite>). The &conduit; package is a
      prototype OpenAPI glue system written in R. Version 0.1 of
      &conduit; (<cite key="hinton2015conduit011">Hinton &amp;
      Murrell, 2015b</cite>) was released in February 2015.</p>

      <p>The following is a simple example of a pipeline, written in
      OpenAPI v0.3. First, the module XML file, `module1.xml':</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/test_pipeline/module1.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module wraps a source script which produces a vector of
      ten random numbers in R, called `x', and labels this as a module
      output. A second module XML file, `module2.xml':</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/test_pipeline/module2.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module requires an input, called `numbers'. The module
      source script creates a plot of this input in R, and labels the
      PDF file of the plot created as an output, called `plot'. The
      following pipeline XML connects these two modules:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/test_pipeline/pipeline.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This pipeline loads each module as a <code>component</code>,
      and connects the `x' output from `module1' to the `numbers' input
      from `module2' using a <code>pipe</code> element. When this
      pipeline is executed by a glue system `module1' will be executed
      first; its output, `x', will be made available to `module2', which
      will then be executed.</p>

      <p>The OpenAPI architecture attempts to improve the
      accessibility and reusability of data sources and computer
      scripts, particularly scripts for working with data, by
      providing multiple methods of contributing to a solution, at
      multiple levels of skill and expertise. The next section
      describes some of the problems with the version 0.1 of the
      OpenAPI architecture.</p>

      <!-- section break -->

    </section>

    <section id="sec-problems-in-openapi-version-0.1">

      <h1>Problems in OpenAPI version 0.1</h1>

      <p>Version 0.1 of the OpenAPI XML specification of pipeline and
      module XML files was described in Hinton and Murrell (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">2015a</cite>). A key feature of the
      OpenAPI architecture is that it should allow users to wrap
      scripts&mdash;especially those authored by someone
      else&mdash;without having a high knowledge of the script's
      programming language. An ideal situation is that a module author
      should only have to know the names and formats of the resources
      that a script requires in order to be executed (its inputs), and
      the names and formats of the resources it produces which the
      author may want to consume or retrieve (its outputs). Most
      existing scripts&mdash;`wild' scripts&mdash;will not have been
      written with OpenAPI in mind, and so the OpenAPI architecture
      must be able to cope with this.</p>

      <p>In this section we will describe several problems with OpenAPI
      version 0.1, including:</p>

      <p>This specification was implemented in version 0.1 of the
      &conduit; package. This implementation suffers from problems
      with:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Specifying module <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> and
	<code>&lt;output&gt;</code> elements</li>
	<li>Specifying module <code>&lt;source&gt;</code> elements</li>
	<li>Meeting module dependencies</li>
	<li>Validating module and pipeline XML</li>
      </ul>

      <p>We will then describe how these problems make OpenAPI version
      0.1 unsuitable for transparently wrapping and executing `wild'
      data scripts by way of two examples.</p>

      <h2>Specifying module <code>input</code> and <code>output</code> elements</h2>

      <p>The module XML specification used in OpenAPI version 0.1
      requires that module <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> and
      <code>&lt;output&gt;</code> elements have a `name' and a `type'
      attribute; type can be either ``internal'' or ``external''. In
      the following code we see an example of an internal-type input
      and an external-type output:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R"/>
  <input name="a" type="internal"/>
  <source><![CDATA[data <- myFun(a)
png("example.png")
myPlot(data)
dev.off()
]]]]><![CDATA[></source>
  <output name="dataplot" type="external" ref="example.png"/>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>An internal-type input or output is an object which is
      particular to the module's platform&mdash;the above example is
      executed in the ``R'' platform. A platform's internal objects should
      be able to be referenced by a symbol. An object is internal to a
      platform if it can be referenced and accessed by its symbol within
      the platform and without having to pass the object through the
      filesystem or some other storage or transmission format. In R
      these internal objects are common R objects, e.g. vectors and data
      frames; in Python these are common objects like strings or
      lists.</p>

      <p>In the above example the input specification indicates that
      the module source script requires there to be an R object
      available with symbol ``a''; the glue system will also use the
      name ``a'' to reference this input in pipelines.</p>

      <p>An external-type input or output is independent of the
      module's platform. In OpenAPI version 0.1 these objects are
      files on the local filesystem. A module with an external-type
      output will produce a resource at the location given by the
      `ref' attribute; this location could be an absolute file
      location or a relative file location. A relative file location
      indicates the file produced will be created relative to the
      output location of the module when it is executed, the details
      of which are implemented by a glue system (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">Hinton &amp; Murrell, 2015a</cite>);
      `path' attributes are not defined for external-type outputs. A
      module with an external-type input indicates that the module
      source scripts expect there to be a resource available on
      execution, the location of which is available to the scripts
      using the symbol indicated by the `name' attribute; this
      resource location is provided by the glue system when executing
      a pipeline which connects this input to an external-type module
      output.</p>

      <p>In the above example the output specification says that the
      module source will produce a file object at relative file location
      ``example.png"; the name ``dataplot'' will be used by a glue system to
      reference this output in pipelines.</p>

      <h3>Names and symbols</h3>

      <p>The first problem with this specification for input and
      output types is the conflation between an internal-type input's
      name, as it is referenced by a glue system, and its symbol. A
      module author is forced to use the same value for the input's
      `name' as the symbol used in the source scripts to access this
      resource. This restriction can be seen in the module XML example
      above: the module has an input named ``a'', and the module's
      source script refers to a symbol, ``a''. If the module author
      wanted to call her input something more meaningful in the
      context of her pipeline, e.g. ``cleaned&us;dates'', she would
      have to change the symbol reference throughout the source
      scripts to ``cleaned&us;dates'':</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R"/>
  <input name="cleaned_dates" type="internal"/>
  <source><![CDATA[data <- myFun(cleaned_dates)
    ...
  ]]]]><![CDATA[></source>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>Alternatively, she could prepend the source script with a line
      assigning her preferred name to the symbol used in the source
      script, for example:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<source><![CDATA[a <- cleaned_dates
data <- myFun(a)
  ...
]]]]><![CDATA[></source>]]></code></pre>

      <p>Now the author is free to name her module input
      ``cleaned&us;dates'', but she <em>must</em> name it this, or alter the
      source script again. This limitation restricts the reusability of
      modules, and forces the author to have knowledge of language of
      any source scripts she might wish to use.</p>

      <p>Module authors are similarly constrained in naming
      internal-type module outputs; the `name' specified in the output
      element must match a symbol available after the execution of the
      source scripts. This imposes the same restrictions as mentioned
      above: a module author must either conform to the symbol names
      given in the source script in naming internal-type module outputs,
      or she must modify the source scripts so as to ensure a symbol
      with her preferred name exists.</p>

      <h3>Passing external objects into modules</h3>
      
      <p>A second issue involves the use of external-type module
      inputs. OpenAPI version 0.1 makes external object resources
      available to module source scripts by creating an object which
      contains the resource location before the execution of the
      module's source script. If a module needs a CSV file for script
      execution, the script must refer to the CSV file location using
      a symbol matching the input's `name' when it is accessed in
      code.</p>

      <p>As an example, the following R script demonstrates how a script
      author might normally refer to a CSV file found at resource
      location ``bigdata.csv":</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[if (file.exists("bigdata.csv")) {
  data <- read.csv("bigdata.csv")
}]]></code></pre>

      <p>If a module author intended for the resource location used in a
      module script to be provided by another module's external-type
      output she must refer to the resource location using a symbol
      matching her module's external-type `name' attribute, for
      example:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R"/>
  <input name="csvfile" type="external"/>
  <source><![CDATA[if (file.exists(csvfile)) {
  data <- read.csv(csvfile)
}]]]]><![CDATA[></source>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>On execution of a pipeline including this module the &conduit;
      glue system resolves the external-type input resource by
      prepending the module's source scripts with an assignment to the
      symbol given by `name':</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[csvfile <- "bigdata.csv" # prepended by glue system

## original source script follows ##
if (file.exists(csvfile)) {
  data <- read.csv(csvfile)
}]]></code></pre>

      <p>This makes writing modules with external-type inputs an
      unnecessary burden on the module author as she must carefully
      alter the source script. Even if the author has knowledge of the
      language in which the script is written it is likely that the
      changes required to alter a script in this fashion will not be
      typical of how scripts in this language are composed.</p>

      <h3>Starting with an external input</h3>

      <p>A third problem with the OpenAPI v0.1 module specification is
      the difficulty of running a module with an external-type input
      in isolation; an equivalent problem is running a pipeline where
      the first module requires an external-type input. An
      external-type <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> element does not
      contain any information about where the file resource can be
      found; this location is resolved by the glue system when a
      pipeline is executed; an external-type module input can only be
      provided by another module's external type module output. In a
      pipeline the originating module's output is connected by a pipe
      to the consuming module's input. The originating external-type
      output contains a `ref' attribute, which the glue system uses to
      resolve the location of the external resource. As external-type
      module inputs do not contain `ref' attributes the glue system
      has no way of resolving a resource location from module XML
      alone.</p>

      <p>Consider the following module, which requires a CSV file as an
      external-type input, and produces an R data frame as an
      internal-type output:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R" />
  <input name="csvfile" type="external">
    <format>CSV file</format>
  </input>
  <source>
    <![CDATA[bigdata <- read.csv(csvfile)]]]]><![CDATA[>
  </source>
  <output name="bigdata" type="internal">
    <format>R data frame</format>
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>If a module author wanted to supply a local file,
      `/home/bigauthor/data/bigdata.csv', as an input to this module she
      cannot do so using the module XML available. The author could
      provide a module with no inputs or sources which names the file
      location as a `dummy' external-type output:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R" />
  <output name="bigdata.csv" type="external" ref="/home/bigauthor/data/bigdata.csv">
    <format>CSV file</format>
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>The module author can execute her new module by executing a
      pipeline connecting these two modules. However she cannot easily
      execute her module in isolation. To execute her module on its
      own she could remove the external-type input and explicitly
      reference the CSV file in her module source script:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R" />
  <source>
    <![CDATA[bigdata <- read.csv("/home/bigauthor/data/bigdata.csv")]]]]><![CDATA[>
  </source>
  <output name="bigdata" type="internal">
    <format>R data frame</format>
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This module can now be run in isolation. However it is now only
      usable at the start of a pipeline, and cannot receive other
      module outputs as an input. Any subsequent user of the module will
      have to edit the module's source script to change data sources,
      rather than altering the module inputs. This has the undesirable
      effect of solving the problem of starting a pipeline from a data
      file by sacrificing the reusability of the module.</p>

      <h3>Files, URIs and URLs</h3>

      <p>Though we have demonstrated some of the issues with using
      external-type module outputs to refer to files on the local
      filesystem, the implementation of the external-type module
      outputs in &conduit; version 0.1 actually treats the value of
      `ref' as a uniform resource identifier (URI). The &conduit;
      package assumes this URI will use the file:// scheme, however,
      no checking of scheme is done by &conduit;, and the value of an
      output's `ref' is passed directly to any module for which a pipe
      connects this output to an input. As described above, &conduit;
      ensures that a symbol referencing the location given by the
      output's `ref' is created prior to the execution of the source
      scripts; the script author is responsible for deciding how to
      handle this resource location, and whether to handle it using
      file://, http://, https://, some other URI scheme, or even as a
      custom character string. A glue system cannot determine what
      scheme is intended by an external-type output's `ref' without
      parsing the value given.</p>
      
      <p>Therefore, although Hinton and Murrell (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">2015a</cite>) did not document this
      fact, it is possible in &conduit; version 0.1 to provide URLs as
      external-type module outputs, and for these to be consumed by
      external-type module inputs. For the same reason mentioned above
      it is not possible to execute a module which requires an
      external-type input referencing a URL in isolation, nor to begin
      a pipeline from a URL data source without a dummy module naming
      a URL output.</p>

      <h2>Specifying module <code>source</code> elements</h2>

      <p>The module XML specification implemented in OpenAPI version
      0.1 uses a `ref' attribute in its <code>&lt;source&gt;</code>
      elements in a similar fashion to how it is used in module output
      elements: `ref' provides a URI for a resource which contains a
      source script to be executed. As with module outputs the
      resource location provided by `ref' is assumed to use the
      file:// scheme by default, but support is also included for
      http:// and https:// schemes. As with external-type outputs, a
      glue system cannot determine which scheme is used by a source's
      `ref' attribute without parsing the value given.</p>

      <p>Further, the specification for source elements is inconsistent
      between source elements which reference a script using the `ref'
      attribute and source elements which contain the script inline as
      the element's content. It is possible for a source element to have
      both a `ref' attribute, and to contain an inline script, as seen
      here:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<source ref="cleanData.R">
  <![CDATA[x <- runif(100, 1, 100)]]]]><![CDATA[>
</source>]]></code></pre>

      <p>The source script referenced by ``cleanData.R'' might assign an
      entirely different value to the symbol `x'; it would then be up to
      a glue system to decide how to handle this situation, as it is not
      obvious from the specification which script should take
      precedence. A module author would therefore be uncertain of the
      result of executing a module with such a source.</p>

      <h2>Meeting module dependencies</h2>

      <p>The current XML specification for OpenAPI modules does not
      include any explicit mechanism for addressing the system
      dependencies of the module's source scripts. The implementation
      requires the user to set the module's source language, called it's
      `platform', using the <code>&lt;platform&gt;</code> element as in
      the following example:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R"/>
    ...
  <source><![CDATA[library("rgl")
    ....
]]]]><![CDATA[></source>
    ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>If the glue system used to execute this module supports the
      ``R" language, the source scripts wrapped by the module will be
      executed in an R environment. In the above example the
      <code>rgl</code> package (<cite key="adler2015rgl">Adler,
      Murdoch &amp; others, 2015</cite>) is attached at the beginning
      of the source script; if the <code>rgl</code> package has not
      been installed in the glue system's R environment this module
      will likely fail to execute. One possible solution to a missing
      package in R (or a missing library in Python, etc.) is to change
      the source script to guarantee the package is available as
      in:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R"/>
    ...
  <source><![CDATA[if (!require("rgl")) {
install.packages("rgl", lib = Sys.getenv("R_LIBS_USER"),
repo="http://cran.stat.auckland.ac.nz")
}
require("rgl")
  ....
]]]]><![CDATA[></source>
    ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>Now the module source script checks to see if the
      <code>rgl</code> package is installed, and installs it if
      not. However, the <code>rgl</code> package itself has system
      dependencies which, if not met, will prevent the installation of
      the <code>rgl</code>package. The OpenAPI module specification
      does not provide a mechanism for checking for system
      dependencies in such cases.</p>

      <p>It is also very likely that module authors will wrap source
      scripts which depend on specific versions of software. OpenAPI
      v0.1 does not provide a mechanism for specifying which version
      of a language, or its associated libraries and packages, should
      be installed. Hinton and Murrell (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">2015a, `Discussion'</cite>) suggest
      that the OpenAPI XML specification could include a mechanism for
      running a module's source scripts on a specific host machine;
      this host could be set up with the module's exact software
      requirements, and be made available to module users. Support for
      host machines is not included in OpenAPI v0.1 or in &conduit;
      v0.1.</p>

      <h2>Validating module and pipeline XML</h2>

      <p>Although the XML specification was described in detail by
      Hinton and Murrell (<cite
      key="hinton2015introducing">2015a</cite>) only an informal test
      for the validity of an OpenAPI pipeline or module XML file
      exists: if a pipeline or module can be read and executed by the
      &conduit; package it is assumed to be valid. It is desirable to
      have a more formal specification and test of validity for module
      and pipeline XML files in the form of an XML Document Type
      Definition (DTD) and/or XML Schema to ensure the consistency of
      OpenAPI documents.</p>

      <h2>Running `wild' source scripts</h2>

      <p>The OpenAPI architecture aims to make it easy to wrap and
      execute `wild' data analysis scripts in module XML. However,
      several of the problems described above make this very difficult
      in OpenAPI v0.1. We will give two examples which highlight the
      difficulties in wrapping `wild' scripts.</p>

      <p>The first example demonstrates how a simple R script found in
      the `wild' might present a challenge to an OpenAPI module
      author. This script was published on the University of
      Auckland's Statistics 330 website as supplementary code to a
      lecture on R graphics (<cite key="klaere2015stats330">Klaere,
      2015</cite>). The first 21 lines of the script are:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[##############################
### STATS 330/762 - Lecture 3: Graphics
### 23/07/2015
### Dr. Steffen Klaere
### Supplementary Code
### NEEDS: hb1.csv and fever_data.csv
##############################

### Change working directory
# Adapt to your own needs
setwd("<Your Directory>")

### Packages
library(R330)

###################################
### First example, Exchange rates
###################################
exchange <- read.csv("hb1.csv")
exchange[,1] <- as.Date(sapply(exchange[,1],function(x){paste(1,x)}),format="%d %B %Y")
plot(USD~month,data=exchange,type="l",lwd=4,col="steelblue",xlab="Date",ylab="Exchange rate",main="Exchange rate between US$ and NZ$")]]></code></pre>

      <p>As Klaere has helpfully indicates on line six, this script
      requires two files: `hb1.csv' and `fever&us;data.csv', both
      available from the course website; the first of these files is
      called on explicitly by its filename in line 19. These files are
      obvious candidates for module inputs. However, as mentioned
      above, there is no straightforward way of describing file inputs
      to an OpenAPI module&mdash;file inputs to modules must be the
      outputs of other modules, or the module source script must be
      modified to adapt to file locations. The module author is faced
      with both editing the source script <em>and</em> creating dummy
      module outputs simply to provide files to a script. Of course,
      she can simply leave the script as is, and make sure the files
      are in the right file location, restricting her pipeline's
      reusability and modularity. None of these options provides a
      simple way of wrapping a script for inclusion in a pipeline, or
      even for executing the script on its own.</p>

      <p>If even this simple example of wrapping a source script in an
      OpenAPI module seems difficult, then wrapping other common
      `wild' data scripts proves even more difficult. For example, it
      is common to find data analysis scripts, in R, Python, and other
      languages, embedded in blog posts, as in <a
      href="#figure-1">Figure 1</a>.</p>

      <figure src="images/2015-10-04-blog-code.png" alt="A blog
      post with code chunks"><figcaption>Screen capture of a blog post
      containing R code chunks
      <url>http://blogs.casa.ucl.ac.uk/category/r-spatial/</url>
      </figcaption></figure>

      <p>In the blog post shown in <a href="#figure-1">Figure 1</a>
      (<cite key="cheshire2015mapping">Cheshire, 2015</cite>) we see R
      code chunks mixed with descriptive text. It would not be
      possible to execute the entire blog post as an R script; if an
      author wanted to wrap this script in an OpenAPI module she must
      select only the parts of the blog post which contain executable
      R code. Even then the author must still arrange for the data
      file, `wu03ew&us;v1.csv', and any other data dependencies, to be
      resolved as module inputs with all the same difficulties
      mentioned above.</p>

      <p>In the next section we will describe how the problems and
      limitations in OpenAPI v0.1 have been addressed in OpenAPI
      v0.3.</p>
      
      <!-- section break -->

    </section>

    <section id="sec-changes-in-openapi-version-0.3">

      <h1>Changes in OpenAPI version 0.3</h1>

      <p>One of the main aims of this project was to improve the OpenAPI
      XML specification to deal with the problems detailed in the
      previous section. This project has made improvements to the XML
      specification for modules and pipelines by:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Introducing vessels to reference resources in module
	inputs, outputs, and sources, and in pipeline components;</li>
	<li>Refactoring module platform elements into module
	`language' attributes;</li>
	<li>Adding host specification to modules;</li>
	<li>Specifying XML Schema for valid pipeline and module
	XML.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Vessels</h2>
      
      <p>As described in the previous section, the way module inputs,
      outputs, and sources were specified was inconsistently designed
      in OpenAPI v0.1. Module input and output elements featured the
      somewhat vague `name' attribute, which was used inconsistently
      throughout v0.1. This was combined with a `type' attribute which
      attempted to indicate whether an input or output was
      ``internal'' to the module's language, or ``external'' as in a
      file or URL. Output elements had `ref' attributes to indicate
      the file or URL address of a module's output, but input elements
      had no ability to specify a particular resource using
      `ref'. Module source elements also featured `ref' attributes,
      but this functioned as in indicator of a file to be read into
      the module, and not an output produced by the module, as was the
      case for the `ref' attribute in output elements.</p>

      <p>This project introduces a new element-type in OpenAPI v0.3,
      which we have called `vessel' elements. A vessel element is
      designed to act as a pointer to a resource which a module either
      consumes when executed, or produces as a consequence of its
      execution. A vessel is required inside each module
      <code>input</code>, <code>output</code>, or <code>source</code>
      element. Instead of an input or output declaring a `type', the
      vessel element's name indicates the type of resource used;
      <code>internal</code>-, <code>file</code>-, <code>url</code>-,
      and <code>script</code>-type vessels have been implemented in
      OpenAPI v0.3. The following code demonstrates how a module input
      can refer to an internal resource through a vessel element:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<input name="in1">
  <internal symbol="pricelist"/>
</input>]]></code></pre>

      <p>In OpenAPI v0.3 a module input or output element now has only
      one attribute: `name'. The `name' attribute is used by OpenAPI
      pipeline XML and an OpenAPI glue system to indicate a specific
      input or output element; the `name' attribute does not have to
      correspond to the way a resource is labelled within a module
      source script. Attributes of a module input or output's vessel
      element will still correspond to details inside source scripts,
      but a module author is no longer constrained by the naming
      choices of a script author.</p>

      <p>A vessel element serves as an interface to a resource which
      is common across the parts of OpenAPI XML which consume or
      produce resources. A vessel is not intended to be the resource
      itself, but rather a pointer to the resource. In the case of
      module inputs a vessel points to a resource which should already
      exist at the time a module is executed; vessel elements in
      module outputs point to a resource which will exist after a
      module is executed; vessel elements in module
      <code>source</code> elements point to a reference which will be
      read in by an OpenAPI glue system in order to execute a
      module.</p>

      <p>A vessel type can be defined for any type of resource which
      can be referenced by a pointer to the the resource, e.g. a file
      path for file resources, or a URL for resources available over a
      network interface. An OpenAPI glue system should provide methods
      for resolving each type of vessel resource it supports; a glue
      system does not have to be able to read from the resource
      indicated by a vessel, but it must be able to determine whether
      or not the resource indicated by a vessel can be accessed by a
      module's source scripts.</p>

      <h3>Vessel use in module inputs and outputs</h3>

      <p>Under OpenAPI v0.1 module input and output elements could
      have either an ``internal'' or ``external'' type; internal
      inputs and outputs pass objects native to the module's language,
      while external inputs and outputs pass external objects like
      files or URLs. OpenAPI v0.3 replaces this mechanism with several
      vessel elements for module inputs and outputs. The vessel types
      available in OpenAPI v0.3 are <code>internal</code>,
      <code>file</code> and <code>url</code>. A description of these
      vessel types follows.</p>

      <h3>Internal vessels</h3>

      <p>For each language supported by an OpenAPI glue system there
      is support for transmitting an object internal to this language
      from one module to another through outputs and inputs with
      <code>internal</code> vessel elements. An
      <code>internal</code>-type vessel contains a `symbol' attribute,
      which indicates the symbol with which the object is associated
      within a module's source scripts. The following XML demonstrates
      how an <code>internal</code>-type input was described for a
      module input in OpenAPI v0.1:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="prices" type="internal">
    ...
  </input>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>The following XML code demonstrates how this is now done
      using an <code>internal</code>-type vessel in OpenAPI v0.3:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="prices">
    <internal symbol="pricelist"/>
    ...
  </input>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module to be executed using R, with an
      input named `prices'; an OpenAPI pipeline can describe a pipe
      from another module to this input using this name. The `prices'
      input contains an <code>internal</code>-type vessel, which
      indicates that the resource has the symbol `pricelist'; this
      indicates that the module's source scripts require an object to
      be available with the symbol `pricelist'. The input `name' and
      internal `symbol' do not have to match, allowing the module
      author to label elements within a pipeline however she chooses
      without modifying the source scripts.</p>

      <p>The next code example demonstrates how an internal-type
      output is described in OpenAPI v0.1:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="python">
  ...
  <output name="suburbs" type="internal">
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>The following code demonstrates how an
      <code>internal</code>-type vessel can be used with a module
      output in OpenAPI v0.3:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="python">
  ...
  <output name="suburbs">
    <internal symbol="suburbNames"/>
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module to be executed using Python, with
      an output named `suburbs'; an OpenAPI pipeline can connect this
      output to another module's input using this name. The `suburbs'
      input contains an <code>internal</code>-type vessel which
      indicates that the resource has assigned to the symbol
      `suburbNames'; this indicates that the module's source scripts
      will have produced an object internal to the python session with
      the symbol `suburbName' during execution. As with module inputs,
      an output `name' and internal vessel `symbol' can be completely
      different, allowing a module author freedom in naming outputs
      without altering source scripts.</p>

      <h3>Example: names and symbols</h3>

      <p>The <a href="#example-simpleGraph">`simpleGraph' pipeline</a>
      demonstrates a pipeline containing modules which use
      <code>internal</code> vessel elements to pass objects between
      modules. This example demonstrates how <code>internal</code>
      vessels allow module input and output names to differ from the
      symbols assigned to the object in the source scripts. The
      `createGraph.xml' module file contains the following:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/simpleGraph/createGraph.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>The source script of this module creates a ``graphNEL''
      object called `directedGraph' in an R session. The module
      declares an output, also called `directedGraph', which uses an
      <code>internal</code> type vessel to indicate that the object
      with symbol name `directedGraph' is available to other
      modules.</p>

      <p>The module file `layoutGraph.xml' contains the following:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/simpleGraph/layoutGraph.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module requires an input, named `directedGraph' by the
      module author. This input's <code>internal</code> vessel element
      indicates that the source script requires this object to be
      given the symbol `myGraph' in the R environment where the source
      script is executed. The pipeline file,
      `simpleGraph-pipeline.xml', loads these two modules as
      `createGraph' and `layoutGraph' respectively, and connects the
      output from the former to the input in the latter with the
      following pipe:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<pipe>
  <start component="createGraph" output="directedGraph"/>
  <end component="layoutGraph" input="directedGraph"/>
</pipe>]]></code></pre>

      <h3>File vessels</h3>

      <p>OpenAPI v0.1 described any module output or input object
      which is not internal to the module language as ``external''
      type, which was the principal method for passing file resources
      between modules. OpenAPI v0.3 allows for resources to be
      transmitted between module outputs and inputs via the filesystem
      using <code>file</code>-type vessel elements. A
      <code>file</code> vessel element contains a `ref' attribute and
      an optional `path' attribute; the `ref' attribute contains a
      file path which indicates where the file object is located; the
      optional `path' attribute indicates a file path from which a
      glue system should search for a file matching the value in
      `ref'.</p>

      <p>Module inputs which require file resources are described in
      OpenAPI v0.1 as follows:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="suburbIDs" type="external">
    ...
  </input>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>Module inputs which require file resources are described in
      OpenAPI v0.3 as in the following:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="suburbIDs">
    <file ref="151023-table.csv"/>
    ...
  </input>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module with an input named `suburbIDs'
      which requires a file to be available at the file path
      `151023-table.csv'. The input `name' is used by the glue system
      to identify this particular module input, and is not required to
      match any objects or symbols in the source scripts. A module
      author can use an input with a <code>file</code> vessel to
      indicate that a module requires a file with a specific name, but
      can refer to it descriptively within her pipeline without
      altering the source script.</p>

      <p>The previous example named a relative file path, indicating
      that the module source scripts require a file resource be
      available at the file path provided, relative to the directory
      in which the module scripts are executed&mdash;a glue system is
      responsible for ensuring this file resource is available in the
      correct location when the module is executed; this is the
      situation when an input requires a file resource which is itself
      an output from another module. The new specification of
      <code>file</code> vessels also allows module inputs to indicate
      file resources with absolute file locations, as in the following
      example:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="suburbIDs">
    <file ref="/home/biguser/datasets/matches/151023-table.csv"/>
    ...
  </input>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This example demonstrates a module which requires a file
      resource from from the local filesystem, available at the file
      path `/home/biguser/datasets/matches/151023-table.csv'. As the
      file path provided is absolute the glue system does not need to
      resolve the input resource's location&mdash;this module can
      receive a file resource as an input without that resource coming
      from the output of another module. This allows a module to be
      executed in isolation, and allows for pipelines to be started from
      data stored in files.</p>

      <p>OpenAPI v0.1 described module outputs which reference file
      resources as follows:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  ...
  <output name="birdPicture" type="external" ref="Rplots.pdf">
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>Using a <code>file</code>-type vessel OpenAPI v0.3 describes
      a module output which produces a file resource as:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  ...
  <output name="birdPicture">
    <file ref="Rplots.pdf"/>
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module with an output named
      `birdPicture'. This name is used by an OpenAPI glue system to
      refer to the a file resource produced by this module, and to
      provide this resource to other modules' input in a pipeline; the
      file resource indicated by this output has the filename
      `Rplots.pdf'. The name given to the module output does not have
      to match the name of any object or resource in or produced by
      the module's source scripts, allowing a module author to name
      outputs as she likes without altering the source scripts. The
      <code>file</code> vessel's `ref' attribute names the file path
      of a resource produced on execution of the module&mdash;the file
      path given by `ref' should match the file path of a file
      resource produced by the source script. A glue system must be
      able to resolve the location of an absolute file path given by
      `ref'.</p>

      <p>It is also possible for the <code>file</code>-type vessel of
      a module output to provide an absolute file path in `ref':</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="python">
  ...
  <output name="vendors">
    <file ref="/data/plots/vendors/processed.csv"/>
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML example indicates that the module source scripts will
      produce a file resource at the file path
      `/data/plots/vendors/processed.csv'.</p>

      <h3>Example: passing external objects into modules</h3>

      <p>The introduction of a <code>file</code> vessel element makes
      it much easier for a module author to pass file objects
      (previously ``external'' type inputs) to module source
      scripts. The <a href="#example-shellExample">`shellExample'
      pipeline</a> provides an example of this. The module file
      `plotgraphviz.xml' follows:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/shellExample/plotgraphviz.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module requires a file resource, `dot.dot', to be
      available in the working directory when the module source script
      is executed. With the use of a <code>file</code> vessel element
      we can see that the module author can name the input anything
      she likes&mdash;`dotfile' in this case&mdash;and use the file
      vessel element to indicate the name of the file required by the
      script.</p>

      <p>The introduction of <code>file</code> vessel elements also
      means it is possible for a file resource provided as another
      module's input to have an entirely different filename to the
      resource required as a module input. Consider module file
      `graphtodot.xml':</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/shellExample/graphtodot.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module produces an output named `dotfile' which
      references a file resource with the filename
      `directedGraph.dot'. The pipeline can use `directedGraph.dot' as
      the required `dot.dot' by connecting the module output and input
      via a pipe:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<pipe>
  <start component="graphtodot" output="dotfile"/>
  <end component="plotgraphviz" input="dotfile"/>
</pipe>]]></code></pre>

      <h3>Example: starting with an external input</h3>

      <p>The introduction of <code>file</code> vessel elements also
      allows a module or pipeline to be started from a file
      resource. The <a href="#example-fileStart">`fileStart'
      module</a> demonstrates how a module can require an input where
      the file vessel element indicates an absolute file path:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/fileStart/fileStart.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>The input, named `datafile', references a file at path
      `&tilde;/Desktop/iris.csv'. The module source script also uses this full
      file path. In this way a module author can start a module, and a
      whole pipeline, from a file resource on her local machine rather
      than just from a file resource which results from a module
      output.</p>
      
      <h3>URL vessels</h3>

      <p>Though undocumented, the OpenAPI v0.1 supported the
      transmission of resources referenced by URLs by declaring a
      module output or input with an ``external'' type. OpenAPI v0.3
      introduces the capacity to transmit resources referenced by URLs
      between modules using <code>url</code>-type vessel elements. A
      <code>url</code> vessel element contains a `ref' attribute,
      which contains a URL at which a resource can be resolved over
      the web via HTTP or HTTPS, and some other network protocols.</p>

      <p>The use of a <code>url</code> type vessel for a module input
      is demonstrated below:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  <input name="allEpisodes">
    <url ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_The_X-Files_episodes"/>
    ...
  </input>
  ...  
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This examples describes a module with an input named
      `allEpisodes'. The module source scripts require that a resource
      be available over HTTPS at the URL given in the <code>url</code>
      vessel element's `ref'
      attribute&mdash;`https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List&us;of&us;The&us;X-Files&us;episodes'.
      Such a module could be executed in isolation, or could serve as
      the start of a pipeline as it requires as input an already
      existing resource which can be used to start a pipeline.</p>

      <p>A module which produces a resource available over the web at
      a URL can describe this output using a <code>url</code> vessel
      as follows:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  ...
  <output name="episodeTable">
    <url ref="http://127.0.0.1:80/conduit/episodes.html"/>
    ...
  </output>
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module which will produce a resource
      available over the web at the URL
      `http://127.0.0.1:80/conduit/episodes.html'. This output is given
      the name `episodeTable'. The output name can be used by an OpenAPI
      glue system to pass this output resource to other modules' inputs
      through a pipeline.
      </p>

      <h3>Example: URL vessels</h3>

      <p>The <a href="#example-xfiles_pipeline">`xfiles&us;pipeline'
      pipeline</a> demonstrates how a module can use a
      <code>url</code> vessel element in a module input. The module
      file `xfiles&us;season1.xml':</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/xfiles_pipeline/xfiles_season1.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module has an input, named `wikiurl', which requires a
      URL resource resolvable at
      `https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List&us;of&us;The&us;X-Files&us;episodes'.
      The module can be started from this URL, as in the example of
      starting a module from a file resource above.</p>

      <p>This pipeline also contains a module which produces a URL
      output, `season1&us;html.xml':</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module produces an output, `season1&us;html', which can be
      accessed via the URL
      `http://127.0.0.1:8080/xfiles&us;season&us;1.html'. This output could
      also be passed to the input of another module requiring a URL
      resource though a pipe in a pipeline.</p>

      <h3>Vessel use in module sources</h3>

      <p>OpenAPI v0.1 described two methods for providing source
      script through module source elements: by inline scripts, and by
      reference. OpenAPI v0.3 replaces both methods with the use of a
      vessel element to indicate module source scripts. The
      <code>file</code> and <code>url</code> vessel elements described
      above can both be used inside module <code>source</code>
      elements to indicate a resource. The `season1&us;html.xml'
      module file provides a source script using a <code>url</code>
      vessel:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>In this example the module which uses the R language wraps a
      source script resource available at the URL
      `http://127.0.0.1:8080/urlTesting/season1&us;html.R'.</p>

      <p>In general a module source should be able to consume a
      resource from any type of vessel which can reference a text
      document. Module sources cannot contain <code>internal</code>
      type vessels as there is no native internal object defined for
      the OpenAPI architecture.</p>

      <p>Inline source scripts are also described using a vessel
      element, <code>script</code>, described below.</p>

      <h3>Script vessels</h3>

      <p>In OpenAPI v0.1 source scripts could be provided directly as
      the content of module <code>source</code> elements, as in the
      following example:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R">
  ...
  <source><![CDATA[rent.lm <- lm(price ~ suburb + beds, data = aucklandListings)]]]]><![CDATA[>
  </source>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>
      
      <p>OpenAPI v0.3 introduces the <code>script</code>-type vessel
      element with which to wrap source scripts inline within a
      module's source element. The <code>script</code> element has no
      attributes, and contains the text source script for use in the
      module. If the source script contains line breaks or XML control
      characters it can be wrapped in a CDATA block to preserve
      these. The module file `createGraph.xml' uses a script vessel
      element to wrap an inline source script:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/simpleGraph/createGraph.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <h3>Vessel use in pipelines</h3>

      <p>Version 0.1 of OpenAPI allowed pipeline authors to reference
      the contents of a pipeline component in one of two way: by
      module or pipeline XML wrapped in <code>component</code>
      element, or by using the component's <code>ref</code> attribute
      to indicate a file containing the XML. OpenAPI v0.3 retains the
      use of inline XML, but replaces the use of the <code>ref</code>
      with the use of vessel elements. The `test_pipeline' pipeline
      uses <code>file</code> vessel to reference files containing
      OpenAPI module XML:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/test_pipeline/pipeline.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinculde processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>When a vessel element is used to reference a pipeline or
      module XML document the parent <code>component</code> must
      provide a <code>type</code> attribute indicating that the XML
      document is either a ``module'' or ``pipeline''. As of OpenAPI
      v0.3 either a <code>file</code> or <code>url</code> vessel can
      be used to indicate an XML document for use as a pipeline
      component.</p>

      <p>It is still possible to provide pipeline or module XML
      inline. No <code>type</code> attribute is required when inline
      XML used, as in the example below:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<pipeline>
  <component name="m1">
    <module language="R">
      <source><script>x <- rnorm(10)</script></source>
      <output name="x">
        <internal symbol="x"/>
        <format formatType="text">R numeric vector</format>
      </output>
    </module>
  </component>
</pipeline>]]></code></pre>
      
      <h2>Module language</h2>

      <p>Module elements in OpenAPI v0.1 contained
      <code>platform</code> elements which described the platform in
      which the module's source scripts were to be executed. A module
      which wrapped source scripts in the R language was described as
      follows:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module>
  <platform name="R/>
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>OpenAPI v0.3 removes the <code>platform</code> element, and
      replaces it with a `language' attribute in <code>module</code>
      elements. The use of ``language'' better makes explicit what is
      intended by a module wrapping source scripts: all of a module's
      source scripts are written in a programming language, e.g. R,
      Python, or shell. An OpenAPI glue system must be able to execute
      the code contained in these source scripts, but it is up to the
      glue system author how this execution is carried out. Thus,
      while the language of a module's source scripts should be fixed,
      the platform in which the scripts are executed can vary. OpenAPI
      v0.3 describes a module's language as follows:</p>
      
      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="python">
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>A <code>module</code> element must declare a language. Hinton
      and Murrell said of OpenAPI v0.1 that a glue system ``must be
      able to execute the code specified by a module's
      <code>source</code> elements in the platform specified by the
      module'' (<cite key="hinton2015introducing">2015a</cite>). For
      OpenAPI v0.3, a glue system must be able to execute the code
      specified by a module's <code>source</code> elements in the
      `language' specified by the <code>module</code>; the platform of
      execution is up the to the glue system. A glue system should
      still report if it does not support a module's stated
      `language'.</p>
      
      <h2>Module host</h2>

      <p>One of the limitations identified in OpenAPI v0.1 was its
      inability to support various system and software version
      dependencies of modules. OpenAPI v0.3 implements support for
      module hosts&mdash;machines on which a module is guaranteed to
      execute properly&mdash;to address this issue.</p>

      <p>A module host is a machine which meets the system, software,
      and version requirements of a module's sources scripts. A host
      machine should be available to an OpenAPI glue system over a
      network. The initial implementation of module hosts described in
      this project expects that the host machine will provide a Linux-
      or UNIX-like shell environment over the Secure Shell (SSH)
      network protocol.</p>

      <p>An OpenAPI glue system is responsible for connecting with a
      module's host machine. The glue system should support passing
      module outputs to a module being executed on a host machine, and
      executing the module's source scripts on the remote host. A glue
      system is also responsible for resolving output object locations
      produced on the remote host and providing these as inputs to other
      modules, either locally or on other host machines.</p>

      <p>A module's host is declared through the optional `host'
      attribute in a <code>module</code> element. The `host' attribute
      should contain a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) which
      identifies a networked machine on which the module can be
      correctly executed. The implementation of module hosts described
      in this project assumes the SSH scheme. The URI for the host
      should have the form <code>username@host:port</code>. For
      example:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[<module language="R" host="conduit@openapi.org:2222">
  ...
</module>]]></code></pre>

      <p>This XML describes a module whose source scripts will be
      executed on the host a host machine at the address `openapi.org',
      accessed via port `2222', logged in as the user `conduit'.</p>

      <p>The SSH protocol requires that a user's connection be
      authenticated through some method. The improvements to &conduit;
      version 0.3 support authentication using an SSH identity
      keyfile. Authentication via password could also be supported by
      including a password in the host URI, but this has not been
      implemented in the improvements to &conduit; v0.3.</p>

      <p>As a module's host machine is accessed using the SSH protocol
      the machine can be provided in any manner which provides an SSH
      interface. A glue system does not have to be responsible for
      provisioning a module's environment, only for access to a host
      via SSH. A host machine can of course be a physical machine, but
      it can also be provided by a virtual machine
      environment. Possible candidates for providing host machines
      include Docker Engine and Vagrant. Docker Engine is a software
      application for creating and running Docker
      containers&mdash;wrappers for software applications which can be
      run in Linux and accessed via SSH (<cite
      key="docker2015engine">Docker, 2015</cite>). Vagrant is an
      application for creating, configuring and running virtual
      machine environments, which can also be accessed via SSH (<cite
      key="hashicorp2015vagrant">Vagrant, 2014</cite>). Configuration
      files for host machines provided via virtual machines or
      containers can be easily shared. This means that a module author
      could share a configuration file, allowing OpenAPI users to
      provision a module's host machine on their own machine, instead
      of a module author having to provide access to a machine to
      module users in perpetuity. The <a
      href="#appendix-technical-requirements">technical requirements
      appendix</a> describes how to provision a Vagrant machine to be
      used as a module host machine for many of the example modules in
      the <a href="#appendix-pipeline-examples">pipeline examples
      appendix</a>.</p>

      <h3>Example: executing a module on a host machine</h3>

      <p>The `kmeans.xml' module file is part of the <a
      href="#example-irisplots_host">`irisplots&us;host'
      pipeline</a>. The module XML code follows:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/irisplots_host/kmeans.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module makes use of a host machine,
      `conduit@127.0.0.1:2222'. When a glue system executes this module
      it will do so on the host machine at the address provided,
      accessed via SSH. The glue system will ensure that the input,
      `data', is available to the module source script on the host
      machine. The glue system will also make available the output,
      `clusters', to any modules on the local machine where the glue
      system is called, or any subsequent host machines called by
      modules.</p>

      <h3>Example: meeting module dependencies</h3>

      <p>The `xfiles&us;season1.xml' module file in the <a
      href="#example-xfiles_pipeline">`xfiles&us;pipeline'</a> uses a
      module host machine to meet the dependencies of the host
      script. The module XML follows:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module produces a resource which is available over HTTP at
      the URL `http://127.0.0.1:8080/xfiles&us;season&us;1.html'. Making a
      resource available over HTTP requires a web server&mdash;the host
      machine given by `conduit@127.0.0.1:2222' provides a web server
      which can be accessed by the source script when executed on this
      host.  By using a host machine to execute this module's source
      script the module user is saved the potentially complicated setup
      of a web server.</p>

      <p>The source script for this module&mdash;also hosted on the
      web server of the host machine&mdash;contains the following R
      code:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.R" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>From the source script we can also see that the module requires
      the <code>R2HTML</code> package to be installed in R. The host
      machine has the <code>R2HTML</code> package available, and has
      permitted the `conduit' user to make changes to the web server's
      file directory, `/var/www/conduit'.</p>

      <h2>XML validation</h2>

      <p>OpenAPI v0.3 has been described in XML Schema files for use
      in validating pipeline and module XML. These XML Schema
      documents have been implemented in the version 0.3 of the
      &conduit; package (<cite key="hinton2016conduit03">Hinton,
      2016</cite>), as described in this report, to check the validity
      of module and pipeline XML files loaded into Conduit.</p>

      <p>The XML Schema files for OpenAPI version 0.3 modules and
      pipelines can be found on the OpenAPI Validation repository at
      <url>https://github.com/anhinton/openapiValidation/releases/tag/v0.3</url>.</p>
      
      <!-- section break -->

    </section>

    <section id="sec-running-wild-source-scripts">

      <h1>Running `wild' source scripts</h1>

      <p>One of the OpenAPI architecture's aims is to provide a simple
      way of wrapping, connecting and executing existing data
      scripts&mdash;`wild' scripts&mdash;without script authors having
      written their code with OpenAPI in mind. This is similar to
      Berners-Lee's original proposal for what would become the world
      wide web, in which he insisted that hypertext would only succeed
      if it could access existing data. Berners-Lee wrote of
      hypertext, ``what is required is a gateway program which will
      map an existing structure onto the hypertext model'' (<cite
      key="bernerslee1989information">1989</cite>). OpenAPI, too,
      intends to map existing data sets, data analysis code,
      workflows, and outputs onto the OpenAPI architecture. However,
      as discussed in an earlier section, version 0.1 of the OpenAPI
      architecture had several problems which made it difficult to
      easily wrap `wild' source scripts. This section demonstrates how
      the changes in OpenAPI version 0.3 make it possible to meet this
      aim.</p>

      <h2>Wrapping and subsetting a simple source script</h2>

      <p>In an earlier section we described an R script taken from the
      STATS 330 course at the University of Auckland (<cite
      key="klaere2015stats330">Klaere, 2015</cite>). This script file
      was distributed through the course website for students to
      examine and execute the code used by Klaere in his lecture
      slides. The first 32 lines of this script follow:</p>

      <pre><code><![CDATA[##############################
### STATS 330/762 - Lecture 3: Graphics
### 23/07/2015
### Dr. Steffen Klaere
### Supplementary Code
### NEEDS: hb1.csv and fever_data.csv
##############################

### Change working directory
# Adapt to your own needs
setwd("<Your Directory>")

### Packages
library(R330)

###################################
### First example, Exchange rates
###################################
exchange <- read.csv("hb1.csv")
exchange[,1] <- as.Date(sapply(exchange[,1],function(x){paste(1,x)}),format="%d %B %Y")
plot(USD~month,data=exchange,type="l",lwd=4,col="steelblue",xlab="Date",ylab="Exchange rate",main="Exchange rate between US$ and NZ$")

### Monthly rate of change
diff.in.logs <- sapply(2:nrow(exchange),function(i){log(exchange[i,2])-log(exchange[i-1,2])})
xvec <- seq(-0.2,0.1,length=100)

# Draw histogram
# density plots
pdf("data_dens.pdf",width=8,height=6)
hist(diff.in.logs,nclass=20,freq=F)
lines(density(diff.in.logs),col="blue",lwd=2)
dev.off()]]></code></pre>

      <p>The following module XML code shows how this script can be
      wrapped in an OpenAPI v0.3 module file:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/subsetting/exchange_rates.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>
      
      <p>The original script file contains a data input step, at line
      19, where the CSV file `hb1.csv' is read into the R session. The
      module XML above references this CSV file as one of its inputs
      using a <code>file</code>-type vessel element. This input
      has been given the name `data', and its <code>file</code>-type
      vessel indicates it will consume a file resource found on the
      local machine at `&tilde;/Desktop/hb1.csv'.</p>

      <p>The original script produces&mdash;when executed in batch
      mode&mdash;PDF files of plots at line 21 and at lines
      29&ndash;32. However, the author of this module XML would like
      to produce PNG files rather than PDF files, which means the
      source file must be changed. Rather than edit the source script
      directly, however, the use of module input vessel elements
      allows the module author to operate on the source script using
      the language in which the script is written. In the XML code
      above the module author names a module input,
      `source&us;script', which uses a <code>file</code>-type vessel
      element to indicate that the module requires a file resource at
      `&tilde;/Desktop/330&us;Lecture3&us;2015.R'. The module XML
      above also contains a source element which requires a file
      resource at `subsettingScript.R'. The contents of
      `subsettingScript.R' follow:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/subsetting/subsettingScript.R" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>The orignal R script, `330&us;Lecture3&us;2015.R', referenced
      by the module input `source&us;script', is consumed in line 1 of
      the `subsettingScript.R' script, and given the symbol
      `full&us;script'. The `full&us;script' object is then modified
      in the following ways: the data step line in the original source
      is modified to consume the local file referenced by the module
      input `data'; the plotting step at line 21 of the
      `source&us;script' is wrapped in new code to produce a PNG file
      when executed; and the code which produces a PDF file on line 29
      of `source&us;script' is modified to produce a PNG file. Lines
      16&ndash;33 of the altered `source&us;script' are given the
      symbol `subset'. Finally this subset of the original
      `source&us;script' is executed using the <code>eval</code>
      function.</p>

      <figure src="images/exchange_rate.png" alt="time series
      plot of exchange rate"><figcaption>exchange&us;rate.png: graphic
      produced by exchange&us;rates module</figcaption></figure>

      <p>When executed, the module source script given in
      `subsettingScript.R' will produced two PNG
      files&mdash;`exchange&us;rate.png' and `data&us;dens.png'. The
      module XML above indicates that the module will produce these
      files by naming two outputs, `exchange&us;rate' and
      `data&us;dens', each of which references the filenames of the
      PNG files produced using <code>file</code>-type vessel
      elements.</p>

      <p>This example demonstrates how the <code>file</code>-type
      vessel elements introduced in OpenAPI version 0.3 make it easier
      to wrap a `wild' source script in an OpenAPI module. A
      <code>file</code>-type vessel element is also used to indicate
      the `wild' script as one of the module's inputs&mdash;doing so
      allows a module author to make changes to the source script
      without having to create an altered copy of the script. This
      method allows a module author to modify, subset, and customise
      original source scripts to suit the module being written.</p>

      <p>The full module and pipeline XML for this example, can be
      found in the <a href="#example-exchangeRates">`exchangeRates'
      section</a>. The pipeline produces the graphic seen in <a
      href="#figure-2">figure 2</a>. The `exchangeRates' pipeline was
      executed in &conduit; v0.3 with the following code:</p>

      <pre class="knitr" name="exchangeDemo" options="eval=FALSE">library(conduit)
exchangeRates &lt;- loadModule(
    name = "exchangeRates",
    ref = "examples/subsetting/exchange_rates.xml")
outputs &lt;- runModule(exchangeRates)
      </pre>

      <p>The next section examines `wild' scripts which are not made
      available as simple script files.</p>

      <h2>Wrapping a blog post</h2>

      <p>One of the major difficulties with wrapping `wild' scripts in
      OpenAPI is that often data analysis code is not shared as a
      script file&mdash;rather it is embedded and discussed on web
      pages and in blog posts. The following example demonstrates how
      the code in a blog post at
      <url>http://spatial.ly/2015/03/mapping-flows/</url>&mdash;see <a
      href="#figure-3">figure 3</a> for a screen capture of the blog
      post&mdash;can be captured and exectuted by OpenAPI v0.3.</p>

      <figure src="images/2015-10-04-blog-code.png" alt="A blog
      post with code chunks"><figcaption>Screen capture of blog post
      wrapped in `ukCommuterErsatz' pipeline
      <url>http://blogs.casa.ucl.ac.uk/category/r-spatial/</url>
      </figcaption></figure>

      <p>The pipeline example below wraps and executes the code in a
      blog post called `Mapping Flows in R', which was posted at
      <url>http://spatial.ly/2015/03/mapping-flows/</url> (<cite
      key="cheshire2015mapping">Cheshire, 2015</cite>). At the time
      writing the pipeline there was a technical issue with the site
      hosting the post which meant the R code was displayed
      incorrectly, so a blog network feed syndicating the post was
      used in the pipeline
      instead&mdash;<url>http://blogs.casa.ucl.ac.uk/category/r-spatial/</url>.
      As if to demonstrate the ephemeral nature of the web the
      syndicating page changed its format at the time of this report
      being written, which led to the example below to be based on an
      archived copy of the blog post. The original code for this
      pipeline can be found in the <a
      href="#example-ukCommuter">`ukCommuter' section</a>; the code
      used in this example can be found in the <a
      href="#example-ukCommuterErsatz">`ukCommuterErsatz'
      section</a>.</p>

      <p>The following XML file `extract&us;scripts.xml' shows how the blog
      post is wrapped in a module:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/ukCommuterErsatz/extract_scripts.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module has one input, named `blog', which requires a
      resource available at the URL
      `http://127.0.0.1:8080/report/R%20spatial%20&bar;%20The%20CASA%20Blog%20Network.html'.
      The module source consumes the file at this URL, and writes a
      copy of this file to disk as `source&us;lines.txt'. The module
      source script extracts the lines of code from the blog post and
      tidies the code for execution. The code is split into two
      objects, called `data&us;script' and `graphics&us;script'. These
      objects are saved as files `data&us;script.R' and
      `graphics&us;script.R' respectively. The three files created by
      the module source are named as module outputs `raw&us;source',
      `data&us;script', and `graphics&us;script' respectively. The
      module also names two other outputs, `wu03ew&us;v1.csv.zip' and
      `msoa&us;popweightedcentroids.csv', which reference the URLs of
      two data files required by the code in the blog post.</p>

      <p>By using a module input with a <code>url</code>-type vessel
      element indicating the original blog post OpenAPI 0.3 allows a
      module author to not only wrap and execute the code contained in
      a blog post, but also to maintain a connection to the original
      blog post. In this way a module can be updated when its input
      file is updated. Producing the source code of the original blog
      resource as an output allows a module author to preserve a blog
      post as it was when the code was executed. Passing the extracted
      code out as module outputs allows the module author to preserve
      the code content of a blog post in an executable form, which can
      now be passed to another module.</p>

      <p>The original blog post mentions that the resource called
      `wu03ew&us;v1.csv.zip' in the module XML above needs to be
      unzipped for the code to be executed. The module XML file
      `extract&us;flow&us;data.xml' extracts this data from its zip
      file:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/ukCommuterErsatz/extract_flow_data.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>The `ukCommuterErsatz' pipeline connects the
      `wu03ew&us;v1.csv.zip' output from the module file
      `extract&us;scripts.xml' to the corresponding input of the above
      module, which then returns the uncompressed CSV file as a module
      output, named `wu03ew&us;v1.csv'. The data scripts embedded in
      the blog post should now have all the inputs required for
      execution. A module XML file, `set&us;coords.xml', receives and
      executes the `data&us;script' output from
      `extract&us;scripts.xml' above, and the
      `uk&us;flow&us;graphic.xml' module XML file executes the
      `graphics&us;script' output, producing the graphic shown in <a
      href="#figure-4">figure 4</a>. The full details of this pipeline
      can be seen in the <a
      href="#example-ukCommuterErsatz">`ukCommuterErsatz'
      section</a>. The `ukCommuterErsatz' pipeline is executed in
      &conduit; v0.3 using the following code:</p>

      <pre class="knitr" name="ukCommuterDemo" 
	   options="eval=FALSE">library(conduit)
ukCommuterErsatz &lt;- loadPipeline("ukCommuterErsatz",
                                 "examples/ukCommuterErsatz/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(ukCommuterErsatz, targetDirectory = tempdir())
      </pre>

      <figure src="images/ukCommuterGraphic.png" alt="map of UK
      commuter routes"><figcaption>ukCommuterGraphic.png: graphic
      produced by the `ukCommuterErsatz'
      pipeline</figcaption></figure>

      <p>The introduction of <code>url</code>- and
      <code>file</code>-type vessel elements in OpenAPI v0.3 has made
      it possible to ``execute'' a blog post, as in the example
      above. Ordinarily the code in a blog post requires some
      manipulation to execute, and it is almost never as simple as
      copying, pasting, and running the code. As in the example here,
      data analysis code in blog posts can be presented in fragments,
      with data and software requirements described both pragmatically
      in the code and in the text of the blog post itself, as with the
      input files in this example. By wrapping a blog post in an
      OpenAPI module the author provides an interface to a blog post
      which allows the repeated execution of the code on different
      machines. The module file `extract&us;scripts.xml' in the
      `ukCommuterErsatz' pipeline above provides access to not just
      the blog post's code, but to its input files. This allows for
      re-use, not just of the script, but of the inputs
      themselves.</p>

      <p>The <a href="#example-ukResponseErsatz">`ukResponseErsatz'
      pipeline</a> re-uses the input resources extracted from the blog
      post in the `ukCommuterErsatz' pipeline. The `ukResponseErsatz'
      pipeline wraps a blog post, `Mapping Flows in R ... with
      data.table and lattice' (<cite
      key="perpinlamigueiro2015mapping">Perpin Lamigueiro,
      2015</cite>), which demonstrates another method of producing a
      graphic like the one in Cheshire (<cite
      key="cheshire2015mapping">2015</cite>) using the same data
      sources&mdash;a screen grab of this blog post can be seen in <a
      href="#figure-5">figure 5</a>. The `ukResponseErsatz' pipeline
      is derived from the <a href="#example-ukResponse">`ukResponse'
      pipeline</a> to preserve this example against the shifting sands
      of online resources.</p>

      <figure src="images/2015-11-07-response-blog.png" alt="A blog
      post with code chunks"><figcaption>Screen capture of blog post
      wrapped in `ukResponseErsatz' pipeline
      <url>https://procomun.wordpress.com/2015/04/14/mapping-flows-in-r-with-data-table-and-lattice/</url>
      </figcaption></figure>

      <p>The module XML file `extract&us;script.xml' follows:</p>

      <pre><code><xi:include href="examples/ukResponseErsatz/extract_script.xml" parse="text">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude processing required to see this
	document</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include></code></pre>

      <p>This module has a single input, named `blog', which indicates
      a resource at the URL
      `http://127.0.0.1:8080/report/Mapping%20Flows%20in%20R%20%E2%80%A6%20with%20data.table%20and%20lattice%20&bar;%20Omnia%20sunt%20Communia!.html'
      &mdash;the blog post. The source script of the module retrieves
      the blog post, and locates a line in the post which refers to a
      git repository where the post's code is available. The module
      source script clones this repository, and labels a script of R
      code as its sole output, named `script'. As in the previous
      example we have wrapped a blog post, this time one which shares
      data analysis code by embedding the contents of a git
      repository, and provided this script as an output for execution
      in other modules. The `ukResponseErsatz' pipeline passes the
      inputs from the previous example and this data script to the
      module `mapping&us;flows.xml' for execution. The graphic
      produced by this pipeline can be seen in <a
      href="#figure-6">figure 6</a>. The code used to execute the
      `ukRsponseErsatz' pipeline in &conduit; v0.3 follows:</p>

      <pre class="knitr" name="ukResponseDemo" 
	   options="eval=FALSE">library(conduit)
ukResponseErsatz &lt;- loadPipeline("ukResponseErsatz",
                                 "examples/ukResponseErsatz/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(ukResponseErsatz, targetDirectory = tempdir())
      </pre>
      
      <figure src="images/ukResponseGraphic.png" alt="map of UK
      commuter routes"><figcaption>ukResponseGraphic.png: graphic
      produced by the `ukResponseErsatz'
      pipeline</figcaption></figure>

      <p>See <a
      href="#example-ukResponseErsatz">`ukResponseErsatz'</a> for full
      details of the module and pipeline XML used in this
      example..</p>

      <p>We have demonstrated how OpenAPI v0.3 allows module authors
      to write modules which provide an interface to the resources
      described in a blog post, and to re-use these resources as
      inputs to another script, also provided by an interface to a
      related blog post. Wrapping and labelling code and data
      resources in OpenAPI modules and pipelines allows an author to
      update her workflow as these online resources are updated. Using
      OpenAPI as a wrapper around online resources makes them
      executable in a way which is often not possible directly from a
      web browser. OpenAPI modules and pipelines also present a method
      for embedding and sharing data sets and data analyses online, as
      it provides a means for readers to run and experiment with code,
      and to extend data workflows.</p>
      
      <!-- section break -->  

    </section>

    <section id="summary">

      <h1 class="unnumbered">Summary</h1>

      <p>The OpenAPI project offers a software solution to the problem
      of helping people to connect with data. Version 0.1 of OpenAPI
      had several problems in its specification which made it
      difficult to author new modules and pipelines, and to wrap
      existing data analysis scripts in OpenAPI modules. Vessel
      elements, including <code>file</code>-, <code>url</code>-,
      <code>script</code>-, and <code>internal</code>-type vessels,
      were introduced in version 0.3 of OpenAPI. These elements
      provide a uniform mechanism for referencing module input and
      output resources, module source scripts, and pipeline
      components. The use of vessel elements has made authoring
      OpenAPI modules easier, and made OpenAPI modules better suited
      to adapting `wild' data analysis scripts. Version 0.3 of OpenAPI
      also includes the introduction of module `host' machines. These
      machines provide a stable environment for executing module
      source scripts which meet the module's software and version
      dependencies. XML Schema for OpenAPI module and pipeline XML
      files were also introduced in OpenAPI v0.3. These provide a
      mechanism for ensuring that module and pipeline XML is
      valid. The changes in OpenAPI v0.3 were implemented in version
      0.3 of the R package &conduit;, a prototype OpenAPI glue
      system.</p>

      <p>The changes introduced in OpenAPI v0.3 have made it much
      easier for module authors to wrap `wild' data analysis scripts
      which have not been written with OpenAPI in mind. This report
      demonstrated several examples of how such existing scripts can
      be wrapped and executed in OpenAPI. Several examples also
      demonstrate how data analysis scripts can be subsetted and
      modified for execution in OpenAPI in a way which preserves the
      source material, and leverages the features of the script's
      coding language.</p>

      <p>Future work on the OpenAPI architecture could include
      publishing a recommendation or specification for OpenAPI glue
      systems, to assist glue system developers in implementing
      OpenAPI features. More work also remains to be done in the
      implementation of module `host' machines, including implementing
      a standard way for glue systems to authenticate connections with
      host machines. The method for remote host authentication
      implemented in OpenAPI and &conduit; versions 0.3 is not well
      documented, and is not intended as a canonical model for all
      host connections. It would be desireable to implement standard
      interfaces for SSH keys and passwords. In particular, work
      remains to be done on &conduit;'s implementation of module
      `host' machines, including the way input and output objects are
      made available to various machines. There are also several other
      potential candidates for vessel elements which could be
      implemented in future versions of OpenAPI, including sockets and
      websockets.</p>

      <p>The &conduit; package is very much a work in progress, and
      much remains to be implemented, documented, tested and improved
      in future versions.</p>

      <!-- section break -->

      <hr />

      <subsection class="thanks">
	<p>This project was funded in full by an Ockham Foundation
	Postgraduate Scholarship in Statistics. The author expresses
	his sincere thanks to the Ockham Foundation for making this
	work possible.</p>
      </subsection>

    </section>

    <hr/>
    <section class="references">
      <h1 class="unnumbered">References</h1>
      <!-- citations not included in main text -->
      <cite key="w3c2008extensible"/>
      <xi:include href="references.html">
	<xi:fallback>xinclude references.html</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </section>

    <!-- section break -->

    <appendix id="appendix-technical-requirements">
      <h1>Technical requirements</h1>

      <p>The sections of R code demonstrated in this report were
      executed in R version 3.2.3 (<cite key="rcore2015">R Core Team,
      2015</cite>) on an Ubuntu Linux 15.10 (<cite
      key="ubuntu2015">Ubuntu, 2015</cite>) 64-bit machine.</p>

      <p>Version 0.3 of the &conduit; package (<cite
      key="hinton2016conduit03">Hinton, 2016</cite>) was used to
      execute the pipeline examples in this report. The &conduit;
      package requires the following R packages:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><code>graph</code> (<cite
	key="gentleman2015Graph">Gentleman, Whalen, Huber &amp;
	Falcon, n.d.</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>RBGL</code> (<cite key="carey2015rbgl">Carey, Long
	&amp; Gentleman, n.d.</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>RCurl</code> (<cite key="lang2015rcurl">Lang &amp;
	the CRAN team, 2015a</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>XML</code> (<cite key="lang2015xml">Lang &amp; the
	CRAN team, 2015b</cite>)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The machine used to execute the pipeline examples had
      graphviz version 2.38.0 (<cite key="gansner2000anopen">Gansner
      &amp; North, 2000</cite>) installed. The following R packages
      are also required to execute the example pipelines:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><code>classInt</code> (<cite
	key="bivand2015classint">Bivand, 2015</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>data.table</code> (<cite
	key="dowle2015datatable">Dowle, Srinivasan, Short, &amp;
	Lianoglou, with contributions from Saporta &amp; Antonyan,
	2015</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>git2r</code> (<cite key="csardi2015git2r">Csardi,
	Jefferis, Hester, Ram &amp; Widgren, 2015</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>ggplot2</code> (<cite
	key="wickham2009ggplot2">Wickham, 2009</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>gridGraphviz</code> (<cite
	key="murrell2015gridgraphviz">Murrell &amp; Hinton,
	2015</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>lattice</code> (<cite
	key="sarkar2008lattice">Sarkar, 2008</cite>)</li>
	<li><code>Rgraphviz</code> (<cite
	key="hansen2015rgraphviz">Hansen, Gentry, Long, Gentleman,
	Falcon, Hahne &amp; Sarkar, n.d.</cite>)</li>
      </ul>

      <p>Several of the pipeline and modules example require a host
      machine; this host machine is provide by a virtual machine
      running Vagrant version 1.7.4 (<cite
      key="hashicorp2015vagrant">Hashicorp, 2015</cite>) and
      VirtualBox version 5.0.14 (<cite
      key="oracle2016virtualbox">Oracle Corporation, 2016</cite>). The
      configuration files for this machine are available from
      <url>https://github.com/anhinton/vagrant-conduit/releases/tag/2015honsReport</url>.
      This machine can be installed and started using the following
      commands in a Linux terminal:</p>

      <pre><code>## download machine configuration files
git clone https://github.com/anhinton/vagrant-conduit.git --branch 2015honsReport

## start host machine
cd vagrant-conduit
vagrant up
      </code></pre>

      <p>This may take some time on the first run, as Vagrant will
      download a system image, and install the necessary packages on
      the host machine. Once the vagrant machine has finished booting
      for the first time you will need to add the machine's SSH key to
      your &tilde;/.ssh/known&us;hosts file for the pipeline examples
      to work. This only needs to be done once, with:</p>

      <pre><code>## add host machine to known hosts
ssh-keyscan -H -p 2222 127.0.0.1 >> ~/.ssh/known_hosts
      </code></pre>
      
      <p>The host machine can be stopped with the command
      <code>vagrant halt</code>, and started again with the command
      <code>vagrant up</code>. More information on running Vagrant
      machines can be found on the Vagrant website at
      <url>https://www.vagrantup.com/</url>.</p>

      <!-- section break -->

    </appendix>

    <appendix id="appendix-pipeline-examples">

      <h1>Pipeline examples</h1>

      <div id="example-simpleGraph">

	<h2>simpleGraph</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/simpleGraph/createGraph.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/simpleGraph/layoutGraph.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/simpleGraph/plotGraph.xml</url></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/simpleGraph/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="simpleGraph">library(conduit)
simpleGraph &lt;-
    loadPipeline(name = "simpleGraph",
                 ref = "examples/simpleGraph/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(simpleGraph)
file.exists("pipelines/simpleGraph/plotGraph/example.png")
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="simpleGraphCleanup"
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## simpleGraph cleanup
file.copy(outputs$plotGraph$example.png$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "example.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>
	
	<figure src="pipelines/simpleGraph/plotGraph/example.png"
	alt="Node and edge graph produced by simpleGraph
	pipeline"><figcaption>example.png: graphic produced by
	simpleGraph pipeline</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-shellExample">
	<h2>shellExample</h2>
	
	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/shellExample/createGraph.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/shellExample/graphtodot.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/shellExample/plotgraphviz.xml</url></li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/shellExample/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>
	
	<pre class="knitr" name="shellExample">library(conduit)
shellExample &lt;-
    loadPipeline(name = "shellExample",
                 ref = "examples/shellExample/pipeline.xml")
output &lt;- runPipeline(shellExample)
file.exists("pipelines/shellExample/plotgraphviz/simpleGraph.png")
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="shellExampleCleanup" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## shellExample cleanup
file.copy(output$plotgraphviz$simpleGraph.png$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "simpleGraph.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/simpleGraph.png" alt="node and edge
	graph"><figcaption>simpleGraph.png: graphic produced by
	shellExample pipeline</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-fileStart">
	<h2>fileStart</h2>
	
	<p>Module: <url>examples/fileStart/fileStart.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute module in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="fileStartPrep"
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## fileStart prep
irisfile &lt;- "~/Desktop/iris.csv"
write.csv(iris, irisfile)
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="fileStart">library(conduit)
fileStart &lt;-
    loadModule(name = "fileStart",
               ref = "examples/fileStart/fileStart.xml")
outputs &lt;- runModule(fileStart, targetDirectory = "modules")
file.exists(outputs$species$object) 
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="fileStartClean"
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## fileStart cleanup
file.copy(outputs$fileStart$object,
          file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
                    "Rplot001.png"),
                    overwrite = TRUE)
file.remove(irisfile) 
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/Rplot001.png" alt="pie
	chart"><figcaption>Rplot001.png: graphic produced by fileStart
	module</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-xfiles_pipeline">
	<h2>xfiles&us;pipeline</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/xfiles_pipeline/xfiles_season1.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.xml</url></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Source script found at
	http://127.0.0.1:8080/urlTesting/season1&us;html.R:
	<url>examples/xfiles_pipeline/season1_html.R</url></p>
	
	<p>Pipeline:
	<url>examples/xfiles_pipeline/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="xfiles_pipeline">library(conduit)
xfiles_pipeline &lt;-
    loadPipeline(name = "xfiles_pipeline",
                 ref = "examples/xfiles_pipeline/pipeline.xml")
output &lt;- runPipeline(xfiles_pipeline)
RCurl::url.exists(output$season1_html$season1_html$object)
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/2015-10-28-urlOutput.png" alt="screen grab
	of X Files season 1 web
	page"><figcaption>xfiles&us;season1.html: web page produced by
	xfiles&us;pipeline</figcaption></figure>
      </div>
      
      <div id="example-irisplots_host">
	<h2>irisplots&us;host</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/irisplots_host/irisdata.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/irisplots_host/kmeans.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/irisplots_host/scattermatrix.xml</url></li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/irisplots_host/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="irisplots_host">library(conduit)
irisplots_host &lt;-
    loadPipeline(name = "irisplots_host",
                 ref = "examples/irisplots_host/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(irisplots_host)
file.exists(outputs$scattermatrix$scattermatrix.png$object)
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="irisplots_hostCleanup" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">file.copy(outputs$scattermatrix$scattermatrix.png$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "scattermatrix.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/scattermatrix.png" alt="scattermatrix
	plot"><figcaption>scattermatrix.png: graphic produced by
	irisplots&us;host</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-exchangeRates">
	<h2>exchangeRates</h2>

	<p>Module: <url>examples/subsetting/exchange_rates.xml</url></p>

	<p>Source script:
	<url>examples/subsetting/subsettingScript.R</url></p>

	<h3>Execute module in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="exchangeRatesPrep" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## exhangeRatesPrep
csvfile &lt;- "~/Desktop/hb1.csv"
scriptfile &lt;- "~/Desktop/330_Lecture3_2015.R"
file.copy("examples/subsetting/hb1.csv", csvfile, overwrite = TRUE)
file.copy("examples/subsetting/330_Lecture3_2015.R", scriptfile,
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="exchangeRates">library(conduit)
exchangeRates &lt;- loadModule(
    name = "exchangeRates",
    ref = "examples/subsetting/exchange_rates.xml")
outputs &lt;- runModule(exchangeRates, targetDirectory = "modules")
file.exists(outputs$exchange_rate$object)
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="exchangeRatesCleanup" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## exchangeRatesCleanup
file.copy(outputs$exchange_rate$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "exchange_rate.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
file.remove(csvfile)
file.remove(scriptfile)
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/exchange_rate.png" alt="time series plot
	of exchange rate"><figcaption>exchange&us;rate.png: graphic
	produced by exchange&us;rates module</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-ukCommuter">
	<h2>ukCommuter</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuter/extract_flow_data.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuter/extract_scripts.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuter/retrieve_centroids.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuter/set_coords.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuter/uk_flow_graphic.xml</url></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/ukCommuter/pipeline.xml</url></p>
      </div>

      <div id="example-ukCommuterErsatz">
	<h2>ukCommuterErsatz</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/extract_flow_data.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/extract_scripts.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/retrieve_centroids.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/set_coords.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/uk_flow_graphic.xml</url></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/ukCommuterErsatz/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="ukCommuterErsatz">library(conduit)
ukCommuterErsatz &lt;- loadPipeline("ukCommuterErsatz",
                                    "examples/ukCommuterErsatz/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(ukCommuterErsatz, targetDirectory = tempdir())
file.exists(outputs$uk_flow_graphic$pngfile$object)
	</pre>
	
	<pre class="knitr" name="ukCommuterErsatzCleanup" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## ukCommuterErsartz cleanup
file.copy(outputs$uk_flow_graphic$pngfile$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "ukCommuterGraphic.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>

	<figure src="images/ukCommuterGraphic.png" alt="map of UK
	commuter routes"><figcaption>ukCommuterGraphic.png: graphic
	produced by ukCommuterErsatz pipeline</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

      <div id="example-ukResponse">
	<h2>ukResponse</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponse/extract_flow_data.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponse/extract_script.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponse/mapping_flows.xml</url></li>
	<li><url>examples/ukResponse/retrieve_centroids.xml</url></li> </ul>

	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/ukResponse/pipeline.xml</url></p>
      </div>

      <div id="example-ukResponseErsatz">
	<h2>ukResponseErsatz</h2>

	<p>Modules:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponseErsatz/extract_flow_data.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponseErsatz/extract_script.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponseErsatz/mapping_flows.xml</url></li>
	  <li><url>examples/ukResponseErsatz/retrieve_centroids.xml</url></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Pipeline: <url>examples/ukResponseErsatz/pipeline.xml</url></p>

	<h3>Execute pipeline in &conduit;</h3>

	<pre class="knitr" name="ukResponseErsatz">library(conduit)
ukResponseErsatz &lt;- loadPipeline("ukResponseErsatz",
                                    "examples/ukResponseErsatz/pipeline.xml")
outputs &lt;- runPipeline(ukResponseErsatz, targetDirectory = tempdir())
file.exists(outputs$mapping_flows$plot$object)
	</pre>

	<pre class="knitr" name="ukResponseErsatzCleanup" 
	     options="echo=FALSE, results='hide'">## ukResponseErsatz cleanup
file.copy(outputs$mapping_flows$plot$object,
file.path("~/uoastorage/openapi/documentation/report/images",
          "ukResponseGraphic.png"),
          overwrite = TRUE)
	</pre>
	
	<figure src="images/ukResponseGraphic.png" alt="map of UK
	commuter routes"><figcaption>ukResponseGraphic.png: graphic
	produced by ukResponseErsatz pipeline</figcaption></figure>
      </div>

    </appendix>

    <hr/>

    <div><p><a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><img
    alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
    src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by/4.0/88x31.png" /></a><br
    /><span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    property="dct:title">OpenAPI version 0.3: Improving the OpenAPI
    architecture</span> by <span
    xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#"
    property="cc:attributionName">Ashley Noel Hinton and Paul
    Murrell</span> is licensed under a <a rel="license"
    href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</a>.</p></div>

  </body>
  
</document>
